Preliminary Inventory to the Stefan Thomas Possony papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Stefan Thomas Possony papers
1939-1994
78040
Hoover Institution Archives
315 manuscript boxes, 5 cubic foot boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 16 card file boxes, 1 oversize folder (138.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, reports, research notes, bibliographic card files, and printed matter relating to military science, technology, national defense, international relations, Soviet foreign policy, revolution in the twentieth century, and communism.
Possony, Stefan Thomas, 1913-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
American political scientist.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, reports, research notes, bibliographic card files, and printed matter relating to military science, technology, national defense, international relations, Soviet foreign policy, revolution in the twentieth century, and communism.
Communism.; International relations.; Military art and science.; Revolutions.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations.; Soviet Union.; World politics.
- Material not yet described (Boxes 1-31)
- Lenin: The Compulsive Revolutionary (Boxes 32-40)
- South Africa's case at the International Court of Justice (Boxes 41-50)
- "The Polygraph and Resurrection" (Box 51)
- "Africa" (Box 51)
- "Dispute over the Negro Intellect" (Box 51)
- The Geography of Intellect, including files on psychology (Boxes 51-52)
- "Aggression and Self Defense. The Legality of US Action in South Vietnam" (Box 52)
- "The Nationality Question" (Boxes 53-55)
- "Tecos" material (Box 55)
- Waking the Giant (Boxes 56-57)
- Victims of Politics (Boxes 58-59)
- Testimony before the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee (before Berkeley riots), 1965 May 17 (Box 59)
- Miscellaneous manuscripts, articles, speeches, reviews, conference papers, and writings by others (Boxes 60-104)
- Correspondence (Boxes 105-112)
- Translation on USSR military affairs - US Department of Commerce (Boxes 113-115)
- Microform of captured German documents (Foreign Office documents from the National Archives) (Boxes 115-119)
- Miscellaneous, including photographs of Saigon bookstores (Box 120)
- "The Polygraph and Resurrection" (Boxes 121-122)
- "Transportation and Focal War" (Box 122)
- Lenin: The Compulsive Revolutionary, clippings and research cards (Boxes 122-125)
- Die Kriegsschuldfrage (research cards) (Box 125)
- Strategie des Friedens (Box 126)
- Draft report on Africa, 1959 December (Box 126)
- Notes on equality, 1974 (Box 126)
- The decay of an ideology, preliminary notes, 1975 March 26 (Box 126)
- Paper on intelligence, 1976 February 12 (Box 126)
- Thailand's Kra Canal project (with General Edward Black) (Box 127)
- Space and test ban matters (Box 128)
- WACL conferences, 1972-1974, 1983-1984 (Box 129)
- European Forum, Alpbach, Austria, 1984 (Box 129)
- Miscellaneous manuscripts, articles, speeches, reviews, conference papers (Boxes 130-141)
- Manuscript (partial) under alias of Peter Lawrence Riley on Soviet affairs, with accompanying letters (Box 141)
- Writings and conference papers by others and printed matter (Boxes 142-146)
- Miscellaneous lists pertaining to Possony's work (Box 146)
- Publicity clips (Box 147)
- Research cards: Possony's method of preparing for lectures and seminars (Box 148)
- Research cards: Listed publications and articles sent for publication (Box 148)
- Research cards: Selective catalog of Possony's private library (Box 149)
- Books received by Possony from the Stanford Library (Box 150)
- Correspondence, including manuscripts (Boxes 151-159)
- "The Politics in Mozart's Operas," manuscript and research materials (Boxes 160-161)
- "Parsifal" manuscript (Box 161)
- "Tecos" manuscript and research material (Boxes 162-164)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes the original Spanish version of the book Plot against the Church: Complot contra la Iglesia, US Catholic Conference materials, and WACL conferences, 1972, 1974.
- "Revolution" (Box 164)
- "1848," dictated, circa 1970 (Box 164)
- "The Polygraph and Resurrection" (Box 164)
- Die Kriegsschuldfrage research materials (Box 165)
- "Regionalization of the USSR" (Box 166)
- "Energy Requirements for Target Selection," TRW, 1981 July 12 (Box 167)
- "Disinformation on the Defense," AAAS meeting, 1981 January 3-8 (Box 167)
- "The Spirit and the Ghost" (Box 167)
  Includes correspondence with the Naval Institute.
- Draft for Hoover Institution's Yearbook on International Communist Affairs (Box 167)
- Papers for the International Strategic Studies Association Strategy Banquet Conferences (Box 167)
- "Military Space Conference on European Problems,", 1981 April 8 (Box 167)
- Defense and Foreign Affairs Daily articles, 1979-1982, 1984 (Box 167)
- Defense and Foreign Affairs Daily, printed copies with articles, 1974-1984 (Boxes 167-168)
- Writings, 1972-1973 (Boxes 168-171)
- Testimony before the International Commission on Marihuana and Drug Abuse, 1972 July 18 (Box 171)
- Correspondence with Hoover Institution's publications committee, 1972-1973 (Boxes 171-172)
- Correspondence, including with publishers, contains some writings, 1962-1976 (Boxes 172-177)
- Memorandum by Possony to Bishop McNicholas (draft statement on Marxism), 1979 May 3 (Box 177)
- Writings and speeches, 1977-1979 (Boxes 177-178)
- Writings and speeches, printed copies, 1939-1960 (Boxes 179-181)
- Proceedings, "National Security: The Demands of Strategy and Economics," Center for Strategic Studies, Georgetown University, 1963 January 23-25 (Box 181)
- Material from Father Jurguz (Mexico) (Box 181)
- South Africa's case at the International Court of Justice research material (Boxes 181-182)
- Research material: Genocide (Boxes 182-183)
- Research material: Terrorism (Boxes 183-184)
- Notebooks, 1967-1970 (Box 185)
- Speeches and writings, 1955-1967 (Boxes 186-187)
- Writings by others (Boxes 188-189)
- Lenin: The Compulsive Revolutionary, research materials, photocopies of German documents (Box 190)
- "Bolshevik Revolution Project," research material and manuscript sent to Life Magazine, circa 1957 (Boxes 191-192)
  Later used for Lenin book. Includes plan of operation and "Stalin: Stool Pigeon or Revolutionary?"
- The Russian Revolution: Research Material by Stefan Possony (4 volumes) (Box 194)
  Sent to Life Magazine and used for Allen Moorhead's four part article "50 Years of Revolution," November 1957.
- "Freedom in the Wake of Hegel and Marx,", 1980 (Box 194)
- "Defense in a N-Dimensional World," published in Will There Be War? (Box 194)
- "Health in Space,", 1981 (Box 194)
- "The Myth of Marx," Buenos Aires conference, 1981 May 26-29 (Box 194)
- "CPSU Propaganda,", 1984 (Box 195)
- "The Suslov Dynasty,", 1984 (Box 195)
- "Technological Surprise or Technological Progress?,", 1984 (Box 195)
- "Soviet Russian Antisemitism, Part I," published in Plural Societies, 1974 June 28 (Box 195)
- "Tsarist Antisemitism, Part II,", 1974 October 8 (Box 195)
- "From Gulag to Guitk," published in Ukrainian Quarterly (Box 195)
- "The US Heroin Market," partial manuscript (Box 195)
- "Maoist China and Heroin" (Box 195)
- "Notes on the Drug Problem" (Box 195)
- Research material on drugs (Boxes 195-199)
- Speeches, including at Velikovsky seminar, 1980 (Boxes 200-201)
- Writings, including some correspondence and articles for Defense and Foreign Affairs Daily, 1961-1983 (Boxes 200-201)
- Papers on facts about various countries sent to Leigh Johnson (Bank of Montreal researcher), articles sent to Rheinischer Merkur, Ethno-Autistic Thinking and published in Plural Societies, along with other articles, 1974-1981 (Boxes 201-202)
- Statement on lie detectors, 1974 June 28 (Box 202)
- Press clippings on Possony (Box 202)
- Writings by others, including research materials, general (Boxes 203-207)
- Writings by others, including research materials, Ryan, Paul B. (Box 207)
- Proceedings, "National Security: The Demands of Strategy and Economics," Center for Strategic Studies, Georgetown University, 1963 January 23-25 (Box 207)
- Correspondence (Box 207)
- Miscellaneous (Box 207)
- Printed matter containing Possony's articles (Boxes 208-209)
- Manuscript and research material (including index cards) on the assassination of John F. Kennedy by Lee Harvey Oswald (Boxes 210-213)
- Research material (including index cards) on genocide for the International Court of Justice (Boxes 214-215)
- Proceedings of the CPSU 25th Congress (Box 216)
- National Governors' Conference, 1964 (Box 216)
- Alexander Sachs (Box 216)
- Joseph Kornfeder (Box 217)
- Manuscript by William M. McGovern (former intelligence officer, then professor) (Box 217)
- Correspondence of Kernbach with Schramm, Wellems, Pabst (Box 217)
  Includes memoirs of Arnold Rechberg on the origins of World War II.
- Writings for, and correspondence with, Die Welt (Box 217)
- White House (Box 217)
  Includes letters from Kissinger, Nixon, and Rockefeller.
- American Association for the Advancement of Science abstracts, 1980 January (Box 218)
  Includes paper for San Francisco meeting, "Space and the Longevity of Man."
- Various research materials and writings on space, intelligence, terrorism, and other subjects, including some correspondence (Boxes 219-220)
- Orbis reprints of Possony's articles (Box 221)
- A Strategy for Peace through Strength, 1984 (Box 221)
  Includes correspondence with John M. Fisher, with whom Possony collaborated on the book.
- "The Big Hole in Psychological Operation," proposal, 1982 July 11 (Box 221)
- "The Space Program,", 1982-1983 (Box 221)
- "Italy: Has the Old Man Been Discovered?,", 1981 (Box 221)
- "Apartheid in India,", 1976 (Box 221)
- "Lenin: The Psychology of Destruction" (not published), 1980? (Box 221)
- "Wizardry of War Prevention" (probably published), 1980? (Box 221)
- "The Rediscovery of Baraka" (probably published), 1979 December (Box 221)
- Part II of the basic material sent to Life Magazine, 1957 (Box 221)
- "Successes and Prospects," written for Military Science and Technology, 1980? (Box 221)
- Memo on genocide in the ancient world, 1980 (Box 221)
  Includes correspondence with Cyrus H. Gordon.
- "The Structure of National Problems" (Box 221)
- "Soviet Strategy in the Middle East,", 1984-1985 (Box 222)
- "Antisemitism in the Russian Area," Plural Societies, 1984 Winter (Box 222)
- "Trojan Horses on the Rhine" (Box 222)
- Waking the Giant reviews (Box 222)
- Senator Denton, 1981 June 12 (Box 222)
  Includes Possony's testimony, "Historical Antecedents of Soviet Terrorism."
- First Sino-American Conference, Taipei, 1970 December (Box 222)
- Memo to be sent to Minister of Defense (Box 222)
- Acceptance speech at Military Academy when receiving honorary degree (Box 222)
- Writings, published in Die Welt, Rheinischer Merkur, etc. (Box 222)
- Defense and Foreign Affairs Daily articles (Box 222)
- Long memo to General George J. Keegan (not published) and correspondence, as well as papers on military questions, 1976 (Box 223)
- "Regionalization of the USSR" (not published), 1984-1985 (Box 223)
- "Regionalization of the USSR," Part IV/3, "Irrationality of Nomenklatura" (Box 223)
- "Regionalization of the USSR," Part IV-Appendix A, "Soviet Irrationality - Decline of Soviet Agriculture" (Box 223)
- "Regionalization of the USSR," three other appendices (Box 223)
- Unpublished manuscripts, 1958-1976 (Box 224)
- "Unvolkung Deutchlands" (Box 224)
- "Slavisierung des deutschen Volkes" (Box 224)
- Manuscript on ideological issue (freedom vs. coercion) (Box 224)
- Manuscript written in Taipei, 1970 (Box 224)
- Statement, Congressional Record, 1971 December 8 (Box 224)
- Foreign Policy Research Institute, five papers (Box 224)
- Outlines for projects, 1950s? (Box 224)
- Writings sent to Bayern Kurier, 1968-1970 (Box 225)
- Lenin project research material used for Life Magazine four-part article and for Lenin: The Compulsive Revolutionary (Boxes 225-226)
  Includes correspondence with Julius Epstein (collaborator for the project) and index and photostats of German Foreign Ministry Archives documents (1867-1920) microfilmed at Whaddon Hall for General Library, University of California at Berkeley, 1957 (regarding, among other things, German support of communists through embassies in Bern, Stockholm, etc.).
- Writings by others (Box 226)
- Unsorted material (Boxes 227-282)
- Russian/Soviet book photocopies (Box 283)
- Vienna State Archives materials relating to the Russian Revolution Project (Box 284)
- Russian Revolution Project (Box 285)
- Photographs used for Lenin: The Compulsory Revolutionary (Box 286)
- Materials relating to Lenin: The Compulsory Revolutionary (Box 287)
- Photostats of The Brain of the Army and manuscript for Lenin book (Boxes 288-289)
- South African trial in the Hague (Boxes 290-291)
- World War II radio broadcasts and clippings (Boxes 292-293)
- Correspondence, 1941-1951 (Boxes 294-295)
- Clippings (Boxes 296-297)
- Correspondence L-Z, 1957 (Box 298)
- Correspondence A-M, 1957 (Box 299)
- Manuscripts of works, including "Atomtechnik" (Box 300)
- Photocopies and manuscripts of Russian/Lenin Project and excerpts (Box 301)
- Original typed manuscript of Geography of the Intellect, co-authored by Nathainel Weyl (Boxes 302-304)
- World War II radio broadcasts of Possony, World War II clippings, and World War II writings by Possony (Boxes 305-307)
- Personal notebooks of Possony (holograph), related correspondence, manuscripts and records of writings, dictation records of the Lenin book (Box 308)
- Material not yet described (Boxes 309-338)